[{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"1. At the end of Raging Bull, Robert de Niro recites one of this actor’s monologues into a mirror. He’s not James Dean, but this student of Stella Adler was the first notable Hollywood actor to employ Stanislavski’s [stan-uh-SLAWV-skee’s] “method acting.” This actor played a character who overturns a basket of oranges when he is shot by Tattaglia hitmen; that character played by this man advises his son, Michael, to “keep your friends close [and] your enemies closer.” In an Elia Kazan film about corrupt dockworkers, this actor laments “I coulda had class. I coulda been a contender.” For 10 points, what star of On the Waterfront portrayed mob boss Vito Corleone in The Godfather? ","answer":"ANSWER: Marlon Brando "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"2. Abnormal clusters of DNA in these cells called Howell-Jolly bodies may develop during hereditary spherocytosis. Deficiency of these cells is common in a disease whose name is derived from its prevalence among Mediterraneans. Another disease affecting these cells results from a glutamine-to-valine mutation at position 6 of a protein’s beta chain. They take on an abnormal shape in a disease that confers resistance against malaria due to heterozygote advantage. The number of these cells in the body is lowered in thalassemias and sickle-cell anemia. For 10 points, name these cells that deliver oxygen to body tissues with the help of hemoglobin. ","answer":"ANSWER: red blood cells [or erythrocytes; or RBCs] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"3. A sexually explicit example of this literary form describes “dirty farts...spluttering” out of Nora Barnacle’s backside. A work of this type by John Keats compliments Shakespeare’s ability to cope with uncertainty, which Keats dubbed “negative capability.” Sylvia Plath’s suicide is explored in a Ted Hughes collection named for this literary form. In a novella, Wormwood learns how to corrupt the Patient through works of this type. While on an Arctic expedition, Robert Walton writes some of these works in Mary Shelley’s Frankenstein. For 10 points, name these correspondences that are imitated by the narration of epistolary novels. ","answer":"ANSWER: letters [or epistles; accept Birthday Letters or The Screwtape Letters] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"4. This empire authorized Jan Janszoon [“YAWN YAWN-sohn”] and the Salé Rovers to conduct a series of slave raids in Iceland, known as this empire’s namesake “abductions.” Supposed evidence for pre-modern Antarctic exploration exists on a map by one of this empire’s admirals, Piri Reis. This empire’s admiral Dragut died at the Great Siege of Malta and served at the Battle of Preveza, where Andrea Doria retreated from a fleet led by this empire’s admiral Hayreddin Barbarossa. The Age of Sail began after this country’s galley fleet was routed by the combined forces of Venice and Don Juan of Austria at the Battle of Lepanto. For 10 points, name this empire ruled by Suleiman the Magnificent. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ottoman Empire [accept Turkey or Turkish Abductions] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"5. This deity declares that no giant is equal to Vafthrudnir [voff-THRUD-near] and counsels another deity against visiting him. This deity protects certain people from danger by sending them to the servant Hlín. This deity’s messenger has a flying sea-treading horse whose name means “hoof-tosser,” or Hófvarpnir [hoff-VARP-near]. This deity’s servants include Gná [NAH] and Fulla. In the Lokasenna, Loki accuses this deity of sleeping with Vili and Ve. Freya is second only to this goddess, who is known as the highest among the Aesir. This goddess weeps at her hall Fensalir after the death of her son Baldr. For 10 points, name this Norse goddess and wife of Odin. ","answer":"ANSWER: Frigga [or Frija; do not accept or prompt on Freya] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"6. This sculpture inspired the pose of the central figure in Abbott Thayer’s A Virgin. Filippo Marinetti’s Futurist Manifesto declares that “a racing automobile … is more beautiful than [this sculpture].” This sculpture originally overlooked the Temple of the Great Gods, where it was elevated by a marble pedestal representing a ship’s prow. It was found and reassembled under the lead of archaeologist Charles Champoiseau [“shawm-pwah-SOH”]. This statue, located atop the Daru Staircase within the Louvre, features clothing ruffled by wind and is missing its arms and head. For 10 points, name this Hellenistic-era sculpture depicting the goddess Nike. ","answer":"ANSWER: Winged Victory of Samothrace [or Winged Nike of Samothrace or Winged Victory of Samothrace or Winged Nike of Samothrace; prompt on partial answers] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"7. After a city in this state voted for a 2014 referendum banning fracking within city limits, its legislature passed a law forbidding cities from making such bans. Although T. Boone Pickens’ scheme to build the world’s largest wind farm in this state failed, as of 2018 it produces the most wind power of any US state. This state’s Railroad Commission is unusually powerful because it regulates the energy industry, rather than railroads. The oil-rich Permian Basin is in this state, which is the southern terminus of the Keystone XL pipeline. This state’s oil industry is centered in the Midland-Odessa metropolitan area. For 10 points, name this state where many oil companies are headquartered in Houston. ","answer":"ANSWER: Texas "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"8. This man made a speech nominating Jerry Brown for president at the 1976 Democratic National Convention. Philip Vera Cruz resigned from this man’s organization after he endorsed Ferdinand Marcos. This man’s brother Richard designed a black eagle logo for his organization. Protesting a preferential contract negotiated with the Teamsters, this activist was jailed for violating an antiboycott injunction during the Salad Bowl strike. This activist joined Filipino workers in the Delano grape strike and fought to end the Bracero Program alongside Dolores Huerta. For 10 points, name this Mexican-American labor activist who led the United Farm Workers. ","answer":"ANSWER: Cesar Chavez "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"1. In specular reflection, a line named for this word is at equal angles to both the incident and reflected rays. The force of friction is proportional to the coefficient of friction times a force described by this adjective. For 10 points, name this word which denotes the force perpendicular to a surface. ","answer":"ANSWER: normal [or normalization] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"0. A poem written in this language contrasts the “golden hair” of Margarete [“mar-guh-RET-uh”] with the “ashen hair” of Shulamith, and begins by describing the “black milk of daybreak we drink at nightfall.” A collection written in this language includes a poem inspired by Picasso’s Family of Saltimbanques, and another that declares “beauty is nothing but the beginning of terror.” Paul Celan’s “Death Fugue” was written in this language, as was a poem that ends “You must change your life.” An Italian castle inspired a set of 10 mystical poems in this language that opens “Who, if I cried out, would hear me among the Angelic Orders?” For 10 points, what language was used for the Duino Elegies by Austrian poet Rainer Maria Rilke? ","answer":"ANSWER: German [or Deutsch] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"1. Talcott Parsons’ analysis of the division of labor distinguished between the “instrumental” and “expressive” based on this concept. A 1987 paper by Candace West and Don Zimmerman popularized the phrase “doing [this concept].” The “ritual of subordination” is discussed in an Erving Goffman book analyzing how advertisements affect our view of this concept. A 1990 book considers J. L. Austin’s theory of “performative utterances” to argue for this concept’s “performativity.” That book by Judith Butler is titled for its Trouble. Sociologists often discuss the “binary” this concept is confined to in most Western societies. For 10 points, what social construct is often contrasted with sex? ","answer":"ANSWER: gender [do not accept or prompt on “sex”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"2. Conspiracies theories arose after this nation signed the Tashkent Declaration with a prime minister who died the next day. A leader of this country vowed to “eat grass” until his country acquired nuclear weapons. In 2004, this country’s top nuclear physicist was revealed to have smuggled uranium to Libya and North Korea. This country began enriching uranium in response to a neighboring country’s Smiling Buddha test. Separated from its eastern neighbor by the Line of Control, this country’s nuclear program was started by A. Q. Khan on the orders of prime minister Zulfikar Ali Bhutto. For 10 points, identify this country that contests the rule of Kashmir with the nation it was partitioned from, India. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pakistan "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"3. At the beginning of this novel, Mary Debenham mysteriously tells a colonel “Not now. When it’s all over.” In this book, Cyrus B. Hardman is frustrated that he can’t find a “small, dark man with a womanish voice.” A man in this novel learns that many women’s dressing gowns are “corn coloured” and “blue satin,” but fails to find a “scarlet kimono.” The protagonist of this novel discovers that Samuel Ratchett is actually Cassetti, who fled America after kidnapping Daisy Armstrong; later, the protagonist deduces that Cassetti was stabbed to death by his fellow passengers. For 10 points, Hercule Poirot investigates a crime aboard a train in what Agatha Christie novel? ","answer":"ANSWER: Murder on the Orient Express "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"4. Heinz Hopf conjectured that this figure is homeomorphic to any simply connected manifold with pinched sectional curvature. Grigori Perelman proved a statement concerning the 4-dimensional variant of this figure; that statement is named for Henri Poincaré. The Kepler conjecture gives 0.74 as the maximum density with which this figure can pack a volume. Coordinates symbolized rho, theta, and phi are used in a system named for this solid figure. For 10 points, the solid that gives the largest surface area for a given volume is what shape, whose surface area is “4 pi r squared”? ","answer":"ANSWER: sphere "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"5. This philosopher’s atomism was defended by a later thinker’s idea of the “swerve,” which holds that atoms can divert from their innate downwards path. In a letter to Herodotus, this philosopher argued that death is not to be feared. A trilemma attributed to this man is arguably the first version of the problem of evil. This philosopher believed that the highest form of happiness is the combination of tranquility and the absence of pain, or aponia and ataraxia. Lucretius’ De Rerum Natura defended the beliefs of this man who taught at The Garden. For 10 points, name this Greek philosopher whose namesake school of philosophy is considered to be a form of hedonism. ","answer":"ANSWER: Epicurus [or Epíkouros] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"6. This religion inspired a poem in which a character in “blue work overalls” chants “DROWN THEIR BUTTS/ CRUSH THEIR BUTTS.” That poem titled for Smokey the Bear is by Gary Snyder. In one novel, spiritual experiences like climbing the Matterhorn occur after Japhy Ryder introduces Ray Smith to this religion. A poem inspired by this religion set on “the tincan banana dock” claims that the title object was “never no locomotive!” This religion is central to Beat movement literature like “Sunflower Sutra” and The Dharma Bums. For 10 points, name this religion practiced by Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac in its Mahayana and Zen forms. ","answer":"ANSWER: Buddhism [or Zen Buddhism; or Mahayana Buddhism] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"7. At high pressures, this element could undergo the Wigner-Huntington phase transition to its “metallic” form. Most common solvents in NMR replace nuclei of this element with its rarer isotopes. The kinetic isotope effect is most pronounced in this element, as its isotopes have the largest relative change in mass than do any other element’s. The majority of cosmic rays are nuclei of this element. The predominant isotope of this element is replaced by an uncommon isotope in heavy water. Isotopes of this element, which contain one and two neutrons, respectively, are deuterium and tritium. For 10 points, name this diatomic gas, the lightest element on the periodic table. ","answer":"ANSWER: hydrogen [or H; prompt on deuterium or tritium] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"8. Dorieus, brother of Leonidas, claimed this island’s city of Heraclea Minoa based on his Herculean ancestry. An invasion of this island intended to restore the tyrant Terrilus ended in Hamilcar I’s defeat at the Battle of Himera. This island’s city of Segesta was betrayed by Agathocles, whose son-in-law Pyrrhus of Epirus unsuccessfully besieged Lilybaeum to drive out Carthage. A request by Mamertine mercenaries on this island for an alliance with Rome against Hiero II sparked the First Punic War. Archimedes, who resided on this island, legendarily built a heat ray for its city of Syracuse. For 10 points, name this Mediterranean island, located to the south of mainland Italy ","answer":"ANSWER: Sicily [or Sicilia] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"9. An aria by this composer opens with the notes D and C–sharp, then triplets on C, then B–natural, B–flat, and A. He used a theme based on the carol “March of the Kings” for his incidental music to the play L’Arlesienne [LAHR-less-ee-en]. In an opera by this composer, two characters recall their time together in Kandy in the friendship duet “Au fond du temple saint” [oh fond due TOMP-luh SAHNT”] Another opera by this composer begins outside a cigarette factory, where the title character sings that “love is a rebellious bird” and throws a flower at her love interest. That opera by this composer includes the Toreador Song and the Habanera. For 10 points, name this composer of The Pearl Fishers and Carmen. ","answer":"ANSWER: Georges Bizet "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"0. This country’s Christian church was represented by Dioscorus at the Council of Chalcedon, where this country’s church joined other miaphysite [“MY-uh-fizz-ite”] churches in breaking from the rest of Christianity. A saint from this country is considered the father of Christian monasticism and was tempted by demons while in the wilderness. During a journey back to this country, a Biblical character had his feet touched by his son’s foreskin after it was cut off by his wife, Zipporah. The Israelites are led out of this country to Mount Sinai. For 10 points, name this country where Moses freed the slaves from the Pharaoh. ","answer":"ANSWER: Egypt [or Arab Republic of Egypt] Tiebreaker. It’s not an ethnicity, but the white stripe of the Five Races Under One Union flag signified members of this minority group. The members of the Kansu Braves were part of this minority, as were the leaders of the Ma Clique. A man born into this minority group presented a giraffe to the Yongle Emperor after one of his treasure ship expeditions to the Indian Ocean. The eunuch Zheng He [“ZHUNG HUH”] belonged to this religious minority, and it is the majority religion of Xinjiang [“shin-JYANG”] province. For 10 points, most Uyghurs are members of what religion that was introduced to China by companions of Muhammad? "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this country where, two years later, protests over increased food prices brought Edward Gierek to power. ","answer":"ANSWER: Poland "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Gierek was toppled in 1980, shortly after signing the Gdańsk Agreement, which permitted the creation of this trade union. Under Lech Wałęsa [“LEKH vaw-WES-uh”], this organization led the anti-Communist movement in Poland. ","answer":"ANSWER: Solidarity [or Solidarność] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This Polish Cardinal was elected Pope during Gierek’s rule. John Lewis Gaddis identifies this pontiff’s 1979 visit to Poland as the catalyst for the formation of the Solidarity movement. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pope John Paul II [or Karol Wojtyła [“KEH-rul voy-TAY-wah\"]] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this wind instrument whose players utilize extensive circular breathing. They are often over a meter long, and are traditionally made from wood that has been hollowed out by termites. ","answer":"ANSWER: didgeridoo "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Didgeridoos are often referred to as a “pipe” that produces this sort of sound. Bagpipes also produce this sort of sound sustained for a long period of time. ","answer":"ANSWER: drone [or word forms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] A long-necked string instrument from this country known as the tanpura is also used to produce a drone. Other instruments invented in this country include the tabla and the sitar. ","answer":"ANSWER: Republic of India "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this man who, in a poem, is said to have “fallen cold and dead” after “the fearful trip is done.” In another poem, he is compared to a “powerful western fallen star” that is “lustrous with silver face in the night.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Abraham Lincoln "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This poet mourned Lincoln’s assassination in the poems “O Captain, my Captain!” and “When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom’d.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Walt Whitman [or Walter Whitman] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Abraham Lincoln’s son, Willie, lingers in purgatory in this author’s 2017 novel Lincoln in the Bardo. He wrote the short story collections Tenth of December and CivilWarLand in Bad Decline. ","answer":"ANSWER: George Saunders "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this syncretic religion whose name translates to “highest power.” Popes, cardinals, and bishops are ranks in its executive body, and its beliefs are generally a combination of Buddhism, Taoism, and Confucianism. ","answer":"ANSWER: Caodaism [or Đức Cao Đài] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Cao Dai is a religion from this country. This country’s largest basilica was built in Saigon during its time as a French colony. ","answer":"ANSWER: Socialist Republic of Vietnam "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] As in Buddhism, Hinduism, and other Indian religions, a major goal of adherents of Caodaism is freedom from the cyclical pattern of life, death, and suffering referred to by this Sanskrit term. Nirvana is the release from this cycle. ","answer":"ANSWER: saṃsāra [or sansara] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] According to this principle named for a Swiss physicist, an increase in a fluid’s velocity is accompanied by a decrease in its pressure or potential energy. ","answer":"ANSWER: Bernoulli’s principle "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] In this low-velocity flow regime, fluids typically do not exhibit chaotic behavior, so parallel fluid layers slide past one another. ","answer":"ANSWER: laminar flow regime "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This “tube” named for a Frenchman is often used to measure the velocity of fluids. It is also used as a speedometer on aircraft. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pitot [pee-TOH] tube [or Pitot probe] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this poet of Amoretti. His most famous work is an allegorical epic poem that represents Queen Elizabeth I as Gloriana. ","answer":"ANSWER: Edmund Spenser (the allegorical epic poem The Faerie Queene) "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The opening of Eliot’s The Waste Land parallels the “General Prologue” of this Geoffrey Chaucer book, which describes April’s “shoures soote” [“showers soot”]. This book’s characters include the Miller, the Franklin, and the Wife of Bath. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Canterbury Tales "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] At the end of The Waste Land, Eliot describes this play’s character Hieronymo becoming “mad againe.” In this Thomas Kyd play, Hieronymo murders Lorenzo and Balthazar to avenge the death of his son. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Spanish Tragedy, or Hieronimo is Mad Again "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this opera based on a Georg Büchner play that opens with the title character shaving his captain. This opera’s protagonist gets revenge on his wife, who is cheating on him with the Drum Major, by stabbing her under a blood moon. ","answer":"ANSWER: Wozzeck "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Wozzeck and the unfinished Lulu are operas by this Austrian composer, a member of the Second Viennese School of composers. This composer’s violin concerto was dedicated “to the memory of an Angel.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Alban Berg [or Alban Maria Johannes Berg] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This other Austrian composer mentored Berg and founded the Second Viennese School. The unfinished opera Moses und Aron was written by this composer of Transfigured Night and Pierrot Lunaire. ","answer":"ANSWER: Arnold Schoenberg [or Arnold Franz Walter Schoenberg] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this political party that was led by the former commandant of Whampoa Academy, Chiang Kai-Shek. ","answer":"ANSWER: Kuomintang [or KMT; or Nationalist Party of China; or Guómíndǎng; or Chinese Nationalists; prompt on “Nationalists” or other partial answers] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This wife of Chiang Kai-Shek helped negotiate his release after he was captured in the Xi’an [“SHEE-ahn”] Incident. Mao famously quipped that this woman loved power, while her two sisters loved money and China. ","answer":"ANSWER: Soong Mei-Ling "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] After the Kuomintang’s defeat in the Chinese Civil War, Chiang and Soong fled to this island, where they established the Republic of China. ","answer":"ANSWER: Taiwan [or Formosa] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] If you’re predicting a stock’s failure, you can take this position, in which you sell an asset you don’t own and “cover” it later. Michael Lewis described the 2000s housing bubble in a book titled for a Big sale of this sort. ","answer":"ANSWER: short sale "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] One of the most important rules of finance is to always diversify this group of investments or assets you own. ","answer":"ANSWER: your portfolio "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] You might use CAPM, or the Capital Asset Pricing Model, in which this variable is symbolized beta. Harry Markowitz’ modern portfolio theory seeks to find an “efficient frontier” given a certain value for this variable. ","answer":"ANSWER: risk [or volatility] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this French biologist who proposed the theory of inheritance of acquired characteristics. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jean-Baptiste Lamarck "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Lamarck’s theory conflicted with this British scientist’s theory of evolution by natural selection. ","answer":"ANSWER: Charles Robert Darwin "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Lamarck’s views are somewhat consistent with the “transgenerational” form of this phenomenon, in which the traits of one’s offspring are altered without altering any DNA sequences. ","answer":"ANSWER: epigenetics [or transgenerational epigenetics] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this former CEO of CBS who resigned in the wake of a July New Yorker article publicizing the sexual harassment allegations against him. ","answer":"ANSWER: Les Moonves "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] An October 2017 New Yorker exposé revealed the sexual assault allegations against this independent film producer, whose fall from grace initiated the #MeToo movement. ","answer":"ANSWER: Harvey Weinstein "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The Moonves and Weinstein exposés were written by this journalist, who also wrote about the abuse allegations against New York Attorney General Eric Schneiderman. He has a strained relationship with his father Woody Allen. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ronan Farrow [or Satchel Ronan Farrow] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this novel discussed by Azar Nafisi in a book titled for Reading [it] in Tehran. Nafisi argues that the subject of this book is not the rape of Dolores Haze by “a dirty old man,” but “the confiscation of one individual’s life by another.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Lolita [or Reading Lolita in Tehran] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This other Iranian author described falsely accusing an innocent man of harassment to distract attention from her lipstick in the graphic memoir Persepolis. ","answer":"ANSWER: Marji Satrapi "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Iran’s first female author of the modern era, Simin Daneshvar, wrote about Zari’s fascination with this religion’s martyr Hosein in Savushun. In Persepolis, Satrapi opposes a theocracy guided by this religion’s clerics. ","answer":"ANSWER: Shiite Islam "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this painting whose primary subject stands next to a bowl of oranges. Despite looking directly at the viewer, that subject’s reflection in the mirror behind her is seen to the right as she faces a top-hatted man. ","answer":"ANSWER: A Bar at the Folies-Bergere "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Critics believe the model for the painting, Suzon, also held this profession. T. J. Clark discussed the “Choice” of a scandalous painting in which a person with this profession stares at the viewer as she’s presented a bouquet by a black servant. ","answer":"ANSWER: prostitute [or sex worker; reluctantly accept synonyms like hooker] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This early French Impressionist subverted the male gaze in paintings like A Bar at the Folies-Bergere, the aforementioned Olympia, and Luncheon on the Grass. ","answer":"ANSWER: Édouard Manet "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this technique used in organic chemistry, which starts with a target molecule and breaks it down into precursor materials until simpler molecules are reached. ","answer":"ANSWER: retrosynthetic analysis [or retrosynthesis] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Performing retrosynthesis on this functional group on an aromatic ring can result in carboxylic acids. These functional groups have a C-N triple bond. ","answer":"ANSWER: nitriles [or cyanides] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] One can perform retrosynthesis on amides to yield nitriles, as adding this compound to nitriles results in amides. This compound is removed in a dehydration reaction. ","answer":"ANSWER: water [or H2O] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this country that experienced mostly peaceful relations with the United States until 1941, when its navy attacked Pearl Harbor. ","answer":"ANSWER: Japan "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This American commodore opened Japan to the West by sailing his “Black Ships” to Edo Bay and threatening to fire on the capital. ","answer":"ANSWER: Matthew Perry [prompt on just Perry; do not accept or prompt on Oliver Hazard Perry] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] In 1866, the American steamer General Sherman attempted to emulate Perry’s expedition by visiting this non-Japanese East Asian city; however, the ship was destroyed by this city’s residents. The USS Pueblo was captured off the coast of this capital city, and is still held in this city today. ","answer":"ANSWER: Pyongyang "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this philosopher who attacked Meinong’s conception of a “round square” being both round and not round in a paper that attempted to solve the problem of negative existentials. ","answer":"ANSWER: Bertrand Russell [or Bertrand Arthur William Russell, 3rd Earl Russell] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This Austrian philosopher of language went to Cambridge to study with Russell and, like Russell, discussed the meanings of false propositions in his text Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ludwig Wittgenstein [or Ludwig Josef Johann Wittgenstein] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Russell and Wittgenstein are both associated with this philosophical tradition, which is usually contrasted with the “continental” tradition of mainland European philosophy. ","answer":"ANSWER: analytic philosophy [prompt on Anglo-American philosophy or British philosophy] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this process in which cooler water rises to the ocean surface to replace warm water that has been pushed away by wind. ","answer":"ANSWER: upwelling [or coastal upwelling] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The nutrients in upwelling waters attract large numbers of the “phyto” variety of these ocean-dwelling organisms whose name is Greek for “wanderer.” Most of them are microscopic in size. ","answer":"ANSWER: plankton [or phytoplankton] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] One key driving force of upwelling is this type of fluid transport, in which water moves at right angles to the wind direction due to the Coriolis effect. ","answer":"ANSWER: Ekman transport "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this son of Shaodian and Fubao who defeated the Yan Emperor at the Battle of Banquan. ","answer":"ANSWER: Yellow Emperor [or Huangdi] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The Yellow Emperor is a mythical figure from this country. People from this country are said to be the Yellow Emperor’s descendants. ","answer":"ANSWER: China [or Zhongguo] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The Yellow Emperor’s court historian, Cang Jie [“tsung JYE”], is known for this invention. Cang Jie, who had four eyes, is said to have invented this thing after observing the footprints of animals on the earth. ","answer":"ANSWER: Chinese writing system [or Written Chinese; or Chinese alphabet; accept word forms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this profession of Trefon Ivanitch, who lies about his relationship with Alexandra Andreyevna in an Ivan Turgenev story. This is also the profession of a title character who falls in love with Lara after serving in the Russian Civil War. ","answer":"ANSWER: doctors [or A Young Doctor’s Notebook or A Country Doctor’s Notebook or “The District Doctor” or Dr. Zhivago; prompt on poet] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] This Russian playwright of Uncle Vanya and The Cherry Orchard was also a practicing physician. ","answer":"ANSWER: Anton Chekhov "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] In this Chekhov story, Anna Sergeyevna visits Moscow on the pretense of seeing a doctor to carry on her affair with Dmitri Gurov, whom she met vacationing in Yalta. ","answer":"ANSWER: “The Lady with the Dog” [or “The Lady with the Lapdog” or “The Lady with the Little Dog”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name these objects in which Viking leaders were often buried. In some instances, these objects were set on fire with corpses inside them in order to help the dead man’s soul reach Valhalla. ","answer":"ANSWER: ships [or boats or longships] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The most famous archaeological site in Britain is this monument on the Salisbury Plain. This stone circle’s trilithons align with the sunrise and sunset on the solstices. ","answer":"ANSWER: Stonehenge "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] The most famous archaeological site in Ireland, Tara, is located on and named for one of these geographical features. Maiden Castle is a well-preserved example of a type of “fort” named for these geographical features built in Britain during the Iron Age. ","answer":"ANSWER: hills [or Hill of Tara or hillforts] Tiebreaker. This scientist is the director of SNOLAB, which includes a tank of heavy water surrounded by photomultiplier tubes. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Name this Canadian astrophysicist. He shared the 2015 Nobel Prize in Physics for his discovery of neutrino oscillations. ","answer":"ANSWER: Arthur B. McDonald "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Neutrinos oscillate between this many generations. Both quarks and leptons come in this many generations in the Standard Model. ","answer":"ANSWER: three "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"B","question":"[10] Neutrino oscillations helped to solve a discrepancy in the amount of neutrinos measured coming from this body. Those electron neutrinos are emitted by nuclear fusion that takes place in this star. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Sun [or Sol]"}]
